How do you recognize the physicality, first\h
and foremost? How would you bring it to mind?
As the necessary basis for...
all.
But that can also be a an abstract idea, like\h
sometimes that might lead you to it, but if you\h\h
just think of... if you just tell a random person:\h
"Think about the necessary basis", you can imagine\h\h
they will probably go in all sorts of ideas\h
and secondary directions. So that means that's\h\h
not quite ... that's like a secondary description of\h
the physicality. So what is the physicality itself?
I would say six sense base, but from...
For example the touch, but not\ha
particular touch but the whole domain\h\h
of touch, touch itself. Is it only\h
touch? The six senses, including the thoughts.
But is there anything specific about it that\h
you can say: "This is what the physicality is?"\h
That you can always just kind of repeatedly find it\h
by attending to that?
In theory I can attend
to it because it's already there.
But is there anything specific like any specific\h\h
characteristic of the physicality that you\h
can just use to bring your mind to it every time?
If I just want to remember something,\hsomething very specific and I just think about\h\h
I just think about red and it can remind me of\h
roses. So is there anything like that, that you\h\h
can have with physicality? That you can just\h
directly find it every time you try to do so?
Anybody else also?
Maybe approach from...
sensations?\h
Presence of sensations, overall?\h
But what if you start attending to the\h\h
sensations as a specific thing? Which\his, as you said, another image? Because I mean, that's\h\h
what most people's practice revolves around and\h
they're certainly not developing recognition of physicality.
By trying not to attend to particular\h
sensory experience, but maintaining this peripheral\h\h
awareness. So actually that was a\h
trick question. There isn't anything specific\h\h
that you can attend to, because anything\h
that you can kind of hold on to in that direct\h\h
sense is going to be a sense object. It's not going\h
to be a physicality. So that's why the Buddha said\h\h
it's like a hollow village that gets attacked\h
by bandits. He compared it [like that], so that's basically\h\h
the body, but the problem is when you describe\h
it in theory it sounds like it's obvious\h\h
but practically speaking when you try to do\h
it, you will be confusing sense objects with\h\h
physicality. So like you said, the necessary basis,\h
or sensations, or... The thing is, these are all things\h\h
that can kind of indicate where it is but none\h
of them like on certain occasions but none of\h\h
them are "it". So then if you start associating any\h
of them as: "This is what physicality is", you fall\h\h
into the trap of confusing a sense object for\h
that-because-of-which the sense object is there.
So you said that it was a trick\h
question with no answer. So could the\h\h
answer also be that anything could serve\h
that purpose if you know where to look?\h\h
Well not anything, because if you\h
just stare at random sights or something\h\h
and you kind of keep going that direction\h
it's never... If you're not\h\h
looking for it in the thing? What can serve\h
to reveal that direction indirectly is the\h\h
the utterance of another, the right instruction,
but it's important to keep in mind that these\h\h
are two completely separate domains. There\h
is no direct connection between your thinking\h\h
about what the physicality is - even if it's\h
right, based on what somebody told you - and\h\h
the actual physicality that's there here-and-now. So you can potentially... it can lead\h\h
you to see it, but it's never going to be a kind\h
of direct relationship like a thing in the world\h\h
that if I just tell you: "Look there" and you look\h
there and "That's it, I saw it." It's more like...
let's say ... let's put it this\h
way, it would be like: "Would there be any sight\h\h
that I can tell you to look at that would reveal your nose within your field of
vision?" The answer is obviously "no", because\h
you can spend a thousand years looking at that\h\h
sight, it's a completely different domain.\h
So the six senses, they don't mix, is what\h\h
you mean? Well the sense organs don't mix with the\h
sense objects, like what the Buddha said with the\h...\h
you will never be able to access the eye\h
through the eye. You will never be able\h\h
to access the ear through the ear. So this is\h
the whole topic of this hollow, empty... Yes,\h\h
but with your eye you can also not access the sense\h
base of smelling things. Yes, of course. Exactly.\h\h
Yes, that's another another external sight. It's\h
not the actual faculty. Okay, but that's not what\h\h
you just meant? I just meant in the general sense:
the thought of the thing is not going to be the\h\h
thing. But again, it's not a mystification, like the "non-conceptual actual thing that\h\h
exists below the appearance", it's a practical training of not misconceiving,\h\h
again, not you're not denying the fact that when\h
you think about whatever, when you think about\h\h
your posture in this room you're not denying that\h
that's a thought about the body, you're not saying\h\h
"Oh, I shouldn't be thinking this", but you\h
are restraining yourself from confusing that\h\h
thought to be the "actual" body that's\h
there. Because you see, there is that level which\h\h
even if your thoughts - regardless of whether\h
your thoughts are thinking about "it", or whether\h\h
they have drifted into thinking about, I don't\h
know, Neptune and the the galaxy on the other side\h\h
of the universe - that thing is still there, and\h
it can never go anywhere. And\h\h
that's what I mean that it's in two completely\h
different domains. But that thing is that\h\h
internal physicality that he started out asking\h
to begin with in this case. Yes, basically that is the\h\h
the body that you have to be mindful of, not the\h
thoughts about the body that you kind of\h\h
just pick up on that easy foreground level.
They will be there, but the whole point is to\h\h
have a recognition of simultaneity of one with\h
the other, so that basically anything that you\h\h
could have regarded to be yourself or you could\h
have regarded to be in your control is going\h\h
to be seen as coming second. And okay, that's\h
a conclusion now. But why is that so? If you\h\h
have these two independent directions, then you\h
just said that automatically means sense of self\h\h
comes second. But why is that so?\h
Can we make that explicit? Why does\h\h
dependent origination and assumption of self not\h
go together? Because that's the whole aim. Otherwise\h\h
it could become a philosophical exercise in\h
clarifying what is now the internal body,\h\h
but there's a practical aim here, namely to pull\h
the rug out from under the sense of self which\h\h
is already, I assume, recognized as suffering, right?\h
So seeing dependent origination is practically\h\h
useful because it uproots the assumption of self.\h
Yes, and even if you don't call it "dependent\h\h
origination", because people might then resort\h
to their secondary ideas about it, whereas it's\h\h
more about presently developing that principle.\h
But yes, so why this uproot the sense of self?
I guess one way of putting it would be:
if there's two, there cannot be one.
So if you see the thought of the\h
body there and the body there then\h\h
there is no room anywhere apart\h
from those two for you to be, to\h\h
"be". Of course. And also\h
where do you find your intentions?
If there's those two domains, so the body\h
underneath everything else that you cannot\h\h
directly attend to and then there's your attention,\h
where is your... intention? Yes, where is your\h\h
intention? Which of the two contains your intention?\h
When you intend, do you intend from the internal\h\h
body from, the physicality? No. Neither. Neither?\h
Well neither from one to the other, neither from\h\h
the other to the one. Right, of course. But\h
independent of direction, where is...\h
which domain do you find your intentions, your actions?\h
On the level of thought. Yes, exactly. So anything that would be\h
I mean as a Buddha said, you wanted to\h
recognize all activities, all intentions you\h\h
could say, are impermanent, and that's exactly how\h
you will do it, because if you don't deny the\h\h
fact that you can do things, go here go there,\h
think about this, think about that, and if you\h\h
were to try to look at impermanence
through your thinking, then that's going to be another\h\h
activity that you regard as permanent. So it\h
gets to be undermined by seeing as accurate as\h\h
this thinking about whatever it might be, even if\h
it's a line with the dhamma: "This is undermined by\h\h
this", just because it's there. You don't even...\hany explanation of like why does it\h\h
undermine it, that's second to the fact that\h
it's already there. So intentions, you are saying,\h\h
are undermined by that internal physicality being\h
already there. Yes, because it's completely\h\h
doesn't know about your intentions.\h
The problem is that because you overemphasize your\h\h
intentions, even when they're the "good intentions", then you forget that it's there.\h\h
You obscure it, because this is like a too
course movement for this thing that's already\h\h
there to be recognized.\h
So that's why, maybe now that it's the time to\h\h
mention it: you can't just from the beginning,\htake a random person and tell them to start\h\h
recognizing their internal physicality.\h
Because their intentions, the kind\h\h
of movement of their intentions, needs
to have subsided to a certain degree. Not that\h\h
they don't do anything and they just sit still\h
for the whole day, but that certain coarseness\h\h
of certain intentions is not there
anymore, so that it may not be completely\h\h
calm and still, but there is room now to\h
recognize this more subtle presence of this thing\h\h
that you were obscuring through your own actions\h
of sensuality, aversion, breaking the precepts,
delight in company and all these things,\h
because all of this - even though theoretically\h\h
you can say the internal body never leaves you,\h
even if you go around killing everyone and\h\h
doing whatever you want, it never leaves\h
you - doing those things intrinsically means\h\h
that you won't be able to recognize it. So it's\h
going to remain not seen\h\h
even though it's already there. So that's why it's\h
it's wrong to say that it's impossible not\h\h
to be mindful of it or something, because you are\h
not mindful of it. That's the
default state. But that's a different thing from\h
saying that just because you're not mindful of it,\h\h
it's not there. That that would be wrong, because\h
it is there, even though you're not mindful of\hit.\h
So it's about balancing the two; not falling\h
into the dimension and into the view that\h\h
it exists only when you attend to it, but also\h
not going to the other extreme and pretending\h\h
"Okay, so it's just there, I can\h
do whatever I want regardless." Yes,  exactly.
So going back to the original question:
if you need to look for a practical thing that\h
will reveal it, probably the first thing you\h\h
would have to see is not, again, try to\h
define the physicality in the right terms,\h\h
because you're just going to, again, descend\h
into abstract ideas, even though those ideas\h\h
may be correct and they may not be super proliferated and elaborate, still abstract\h\h
doesn't mean complicated. Abstract means divorced\h
from concreteness, divorced from what's actually\h\h
present. That's what abstract is. So any idea that you might have about it, it\h\h
will still lead you astray. So what you\h
should do first is... well, what should you do first?
So in theory, as long as the\h
hindrances are there, I'm within\h\h
the domain of hindrances. Underneath, so to speak.\h
It's like this body is covered by this mass\h\h
of suffering and when hindrances\h
are below, then the body is seen as\h"it".\h
Hinderances are below? In what sense? It's\h
like "before" and it's like, I see them from the\h\h
perspective of... Aha, I see what you mean. Well, it depends on how you phrase it. You could\h\h
also say the body is seen below the hindrances,\hmore fundamental basically. Yes. And then\h\h
the hindrances are basically happening on top\h
of that. But see, that would already be\h\h
the result of when you have properly\h
recognized it. So what do you have\h\h
to do in order to reach that point where you see\h
the body as more fundamental than the hindrances\h\h
and therefore overcome them? Practice\h
the entire gradual training to the moment
of abandoning domain of hindrances.
Yes, hundred procent. But more\h
specifically, what would you do?
Let's say you have fulfilled the prerequisites. You've been keeping the eight precepts for months\h\h
or years, you're sense restrained, you never allow your\h
senses to spill out into sensual preoccupations\h\h
and you don't delight in company, you spend most of\h
your time in seclusion and you don't tolerate
unwholesome states, even for a moment. So what would\h
be the thing you need to do to...
Again, if there's nothing that you can\h
attend to, no idea that will directly lead you\h\h
to it, what is the first step that you would\h
do in order to eventually recognize it?
Absence of pressure.
How can you arrive at it? It's felt.\h
Yes, but how would you...
let's say, de-activate or de-emphasize\h
the pressure, so that the body can be\h\h
revealed. Because that is\h
what is covering it up.
Maintaining the right order. Well, but the\h
right order is going to come when you see\h\h
the body. So at first you're not seeing it.\h
It's more like seeing this one point\h\h
when all hindrances come through,\h
which is pressure by anything, and...
at the moment of seeing this gateway,\h
so to speak, it's like the entire pressure is\hgone.
Yes, that's again going\h
to be the result. If you do it\h\h
properly, you're going to reach that point.\h
But in order to reach that point, if\h\h
you try to jump there directly - that might sometimes\h
work, it might not work sometimes - so why\h\h
would it be that sometimes you're thinking\h
about the gateway, the point\h\h
where the hindrances come through, and yet it\h
doesn't really work. It doesn't bring you to the physicality.
Whereas something that instead of\h
like: "Let me do this, let me rehearse this idea, or\h\h
think about it like this", what\h
is something that you need to not do?
Not giving into the pressure to see the body. Yes.\h
Exactly. So if you have the pressure, if you\h\h
recognize that you have this pressure\h
to: "Okay, I need to find this", or any other sort\h\h
of pressure, you need to tame that first and then\hyou will be able to... not even find it.\h
You will see: "Oh, it was already there. I was just\h
overlooking it because of this pressure." So that's\h\h
the key. Rather than trying to find the body\h
so that the pressure will go away, practically\h\h
speaking, more often than not it will be the\h
other way around. Especially if you don't have\h\h
the right view yet, it will be: undo the pressure first\h
by restraining your acting out of it, and that will\h\h
then eventually reveal the body. So just a basic question, like: "Why am I doing\hthis?"\h
"Why do I want to find the physicality?" And\h
if you arrive at the answer that there's just this\h\h
ambiguous restlessness, pressure, craving there,\h
then you need to reign in your mind, hold\h\h
it hold it back from that, and then once that\h
calmes down you would be able to recognize what's\h\h
already there. Because again, it's like that that\h
simile that the Buddha gave, when the\h\h
pond has been stirred up and all the mud in the\h
pond is moving around, you can't see what's\h\h
underneath. And so the way to still it is not to concentrate on some object that's ironically\h\h
going to be secondary to the physicality;
it's to stop giving in to these unwholesome\h\h
activities that may seem totally justified, because
see, I'm trying to practice and all that,\h\h
but again, wholesome and unwholesome\h
is determined by the intention behind it. So\h\h
it's if it's an intention of restlessness and\h
craving, then that will obstruct your clear seeing,\h\h
whether you like it or not. But, again, if you haven't abandoned the even coarser\h\h
unwholesome activities, where you're still\h
on account of these pressuring thoughts, acting\h\h
out by body and speech towards sensuality and\h
aversion, then there's no hope that you can
undo the pressures on this mental level. But if all\h
that other stuff has been taken care of beforehand,\h\h
then you're just left with this and then it's a\h
matter of applying the same principle that you\h\h
did with your virtue. You didn't try to
prevent the options to break the precepts from\h\h
existing. You don't go out into the world\h
and destroy all the alcohol there is in order\h\h
to keep the precept of not drinking, and so on. While the option to do it is\h\h
there you don't give into it. And it's the same\h
when you have these mental pressures. You\h\h
will have the craving to do something,\h
whatever it might be, and in this case to find the\h\h
physicality that's coming through that sense of\h
restlessness and then you don't
try to just remove it, because that's going to be\h
another restlessness, instead you just say: "Okay,\h\h
well, I'll endure this infinitely, because in and of\h
itself it has risen on its own." So if I imply that\h\h
I need to get rid of it, that's going to be taking\h
ownership of it and that's, again, going to obscure\h\h
whatever you may need to see. So in a way you\h
could say, when you no longer care\h\h
as much about finding the physicality,\h
that's when you'll be able to do it.
But you certainly need to keep trying\h
to discern it. It's not like you just\h\h
throw your hands up in the air and\h
and wait for it to arise. There\h\h
has to be the effort, but you realize ninety-nine procent\h
of the effort is indirect. It's the effort\h\h
of undoing what obstructs the recognition and\h
not just to kind of fabricate the recognition.
So would I be correct to say that it's good to practice...
including these pressuring\h
thoughts of finding the physicality into the\h\h
pressure. Yes. Because see, any thought...\h
that's actually the crucial thing,\h\h
because again, if you've been keeping\h
virtue, if you have thoughts about covetousness\h\h
and greed and fantasizing about things\h
you want and hating and being annoyed at\h\h
certain people or whatever, you will recognize\h
those thoughts quite easily and you will\h\h
be able to restrain them. But when it comes to\h
these other things that are slightly more subtle\h\h
and might even feel justified like I said\h
before, most of the time you'll get\h\h
dragged by it because it just feels
so personal. It's kind of like you just almost\h\h
automatically take it for granted. So yes, very\h
much it has to be included, because at the end of\h\h
the day a pressure is a pressure. So you don't\h
want to be justifying it, or kind of acting as if\h\h
some pressures are fine. If you want to overcome\h
the hindrances, which are what obstructs the\h\h
recognition of the physicality, then you need to be\h
careful with any direction that involves pressure.\h\h
Because that's what the hindrances are. It's
any type of pressure. So there's often\h\h
this tendency for people to justify, like: "No,\h
no, I know that I'm acting out of hindrances,\h\h
but I just hope that if this is kind of
the right acting out, if I just keep going\hthere,
eventually somehow I'll arrive at\h
this thing that I'm looking for."
But that's not a very realistic\h
hope and you basically just wind yourself\h\h
up and take yourself farther away from it, and\h
then at some point\h\h
you'll give up on it, and then maybe you'll have\h
the chance to find it. But you can prevent that\h\h
entire thing, you can prevent that entire wasted\h
effort by just from the very beginning realize:\h\h
"Okay, this is a pressure. I shouldn't be acting\h
out of it." Because, again,\h\h
it's not only about the physicality.
If you see\hpressure as pressure, you're also developing
yoniso manasikāra.
That will be the way towards recognizing all the five\h
holding aggregates, basically. Yes, so if right\h\h
now you're being pressured to recognize the body,\hcontemplate what feeling is there.
Is it an unpleasant feeling that's there on account of not\h
seeing the body? And if you take it through that\h\h
angle, that's already mindfulness. It may not be the\h
mindfulness you wanted, but that doesn't matter.
Most of the time that's the better mindfulness.\h
Yes. Exactly. It's the one you need, not\h\h
the one you want. So again, being mindful\h
of your intention: "Why am I trying to do this?" And\h\h
that is the proper mindfulness, the proper\h
yoniso manasikāra, then and there. And if you stick to\h\h
it then maybe you will get to see the body\h
on the same peripheral level, but you have\h\h
to be careful that the attempt is, again,\h
not rooted in the same pressure, like we said before.